RG 021:001, Connecticut Valley Hospital
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut Valley Hospital records
1866-1991
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut Valley Hospital
282.75 cubic feet
Connecticut Valley Hospital opened in 1867 as the General Hospital for Insane of the State of Connecticut and continues to operate. It accepted patients from Fairfield Hills Hospital and Norwich State Hospitals upon the closures of those facilities in 1995 and 1996 respectively. Includes records from superintendents, trustees, fiscal, personnel, patients, medical staff and School of Nursing.
RG021_001
Multiple
Historical Note
On June 20, 1867 the cornerstone was laid in Middletown for the General Hospital for Insane of the State of Connecticut. The name was changed to Connecticut Hospital for the Insane in 1874. By 1879 it was referred to as Connecticut State Hospital. The hospital was administratively transferred to the new Dept. of Mental Health on October 1, 1953. In October 1961, the name was changed to Connecticut Valley Hospital. It accepted patients from Fairfield Hills Hospital and Norwich State Hospitals upon the closures of those facilities in 1995 and 1996 respectively.
See also the.
Scope and Content
Series 1. Superintendent, 1867-1982, includes scrapbooks, 1867-1957; Speeches and publications of Dr. Edgar C. Yerbury, 1939-1956; Reports and investigations, 1898-1949; Office files, 1911-1933; Annual reports, 1948-1982; and Files compiled for historical research about the hospital.
Series 2. Trustees, 1866-1961, includes Board meeting minutes, 1866-1961; Executive Committee minutes, 1943-1961; and Building Committee minutes, 1884-1924; and Reports of Visiting Committee, 1913-1952.
Series 3. Fiscal, 1899-1943, includes Finance Committee minutes, 1901-1943; Treasurer day books, 1889-1923; a Ledger of indigents and privates, 1906-1912; and an Employee payroll book, 1913-1917.
Series 4. Personnel, 1874-1941, includes Records of application and service, 1881-1900; Index of employees, 1884-1915; Employee payroll and service records, 1874-1915; Employee biographies, 1921-1944; and Biographies of nurses hired, 1908-1926.
Series 5. Patients, 1868-1964, includes Indexes; Patient files, 1962-1965; Commitment papers, 1874-1916; Admissions and discharges, 1868-1984; Case history books, 1873-1915 (not all volumes present).
Series 6. Medical Staff Records, 1901-1991, includes Minutes of staff meetings, 1901-1917; Lists of operations, 1917-1951; Lists of lobotomy operations, 1946-1951; Admissions, 1959-1968; Day books, 1951-1954; Journals, 1951-1954; a Morgue book, 1972-1991; and a volume that lists children admitted and discharged, 1960-1972.
Series 7. School of Nursing, 1904-1939, includes gradutate nurses record.
Series 8. Miscellaneous, 1889-1976, includes a log of letters written, 1889-1891; some historical documents and other items.
Series 9. Photographs, 1914-1967.
Arrangement
Arranged into nine series: Superintendents, 1867-1982; Trustees, 1866-1961; Fiscal, 1889-1943; Personnel, 1874-1941; Patients, 1868-1984; Medical Staff Records, 1901-1991; School of Nursing, 1904-1939; Miscellaneous, 1889-1976; and Photographs, 1914-1967.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut Hospital for the Insane; Connecticut State Hospital; Connecticut Valley Hospital
Subjects:
Mental health facilities -- Connecticut; Psychiatric hospitals -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Correspondence; Daybooks; Ledgers; Medical records; Minutes; Personnel records; Photographs
Restrictions on Access
New Exemption: Public Act 11-242, section 37 amends subsection (b) (10) of Conn. Gen. Stat. sec. 1-210 and adds to the exemptions of the Freedom of Information Act any records created as a result of a doctor-patient or a therapist-patient relationship. This closure applies to all records listed below as Restricted.
Patients: Files continue to be made available to patients themselves upon reliable proof of identification which may be a current copy of a Connecticut driver's license with a photograph or current credit card with the patient's name on it.
Families: Section 52-146c of the Connecticut General Statutes allows "next of kin" the right to view records of a deceased patient who was also a relative.
Relatives of deceased patients should contact Assistant State Archivist Allen Ramsey by email at allen.ramsey@ct.gov or send a letter with the following information:
- Full name of the patient.
- Approximate years patient was treated at the hospital.
- Name, e-mail, and telephone of the requestor.
The State Archives will search for the folder and will report the results of the search to the requestor. If a file is found and the requestor wants to view or receive copies of the file, the following information must first be presented to the State Archivist:
- Proof of identity through a copy of a current Connecticut driver's license with a photograph or a copy of a current credit card with the requestor's name on it.
- Proof that the patient is deceased through a copy of a death certificate or obituary.
- Proof that the requestor is a "next of kin" to the deceased patient through a copy of a birth certificate, obituary with the name of the requestor mentioned as a survivor, or a signed and dated notarized statement of relationship to the patient.
Other Parties: According to the new exemption, medical records are closed to other parties.
Record Series Listed Below: Records listed below labeled as non-restricted or unrestricted are open to all researchers who have read the rules of use and signed the registration forms. Since these records are stored off site, they may not be available on the same day.
See the policy.
Container List
- Series 1. Superintendents, 1867-1982
  - 1990-018
    - Scrapbooks
      UNRESTRICTED
      Several of the older scrapbooks are in very fragile condition. A use copy has been made for researchers to use.
      The final two scrapbooks contain articles on psychiatry and psychiatric hospitals from national magazines.
      - circa 1867-1896 (Box 1)
      - circa 1875-1897 (Box 2)
      - 1920-1945 (Box 3)
      - 1945-1946 (Box 3)
      - 1946-1955 (Box 4)
      - 1955-1958 (Box 4)
      - 1958-1960 (Box 5)
      - 1954-1959 (Box 6)
      - 1956-1957 (Box 6)
    - Speeches and publications of Dr. Edgar C. Yerbury, 1939-1956 (Box 7)
    - Reports and investigations, 1898-1949 (Box 8)
    - Disarranged files compiled for historical research about the hospital (Box 9-10)
      RESTRICTED
      See under "Miscellaneous" Selected Historical Documents. May include Attorney General Opinions pertaining to individual patients.
  - 2010-010
    - Office files, 1911-1933
      - Alcohol, 1921-1933 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
      - Annex alteration account, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Bathroom sections (Box 1)
        - North, south and middle hospitals, 1926-1929 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
        - North wing (main) and north hospital, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        - North wing - main building, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Boilers, generators, stokes, filters, meters, switchboard, pumps, 1922-1929 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Chlorine apparatus, 1913-1915 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Civil Code Committee, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Civil service, 1909-1921 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Compensation, Workmen's, 1919-1933 (Box 1, Folder 15-18)
      - Department of Health, State, 1924-1930 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
      - Engineers and consulting engineers, 1916-1919 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Fire protection (Box 2)
        - Fire prevention inspection reports and fire drill reports, 1920-1927 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - Equipment, etc., 1912-1925 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
        - Sprinkler system, 1920-1923 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Information - Questionnaires, etc., 1911-1931 (Box 2, Folder 5-9)
      - Johnson & Burns, Inc., Architects, 1911-1918 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Legislative matters, 1919-1921 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Mental hygiene, 1924-1929 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Nurse's home, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Priority correspondence, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Public health service, 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Reception hospital: Construction, etc., 1919-1924 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
      - Soldiers, 1918-1929 (Box 2, Folder 18-20)
      - Supplies, Surplus Army, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Training school for nurses, 1917-1929 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Venturi meter, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Window guards, 1920-1926 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Annual reports, 1948-1962, 1971-1982 (Box 3)
- Series 2. Trustees, 1866-1961; 1990-018
  - Minutes of Board Meetings
    - 1866 July 6 - 1913 April 9 (Box 1)
    - 1913 July 9 - 1920 April 14 (Box 2)
    - 1920 July 14 - 1946 June 3 (Box 2)
    - 1946 July 10 - 1961 April 26 (Box 3)
  - Minutes of Executive Committee
    - 1943 April 21 - 1954 May 20 (Box 4)
    - 1954 July 21 - 1961 May 17 (Box 5)
  - Minutes of Building Committee
    - 1884 May 19 - 1896 August 26 (Box 6)
    - 1922 April 17 - 1924 March 27 (Box 6)
  - Reports of Visiting Committee, 1913-1952 (Box 6)
- Series 3. Fiscal, 1889-1943; 1990-018
  - Minutes of Finance Committee meetings
    - 1901 October 5 - 1911 October 4 (Box 1)
    - 1911 November 8 - 1918 June 25 (Box 2)
    - 1918 July 3 - 1923 July 6 (Box 3)
    - 1923 August 6 - 1929 October 4 (Box 4)
    - 1929 November 18 - 1943 March 10 (Box 5)
  - Treasurer's day books
    - 1889 September 3 - 1891 January 26 (Box 6)
    - 1918 March - 1923 May (Box 7)
  - Ledger of indigents and privates, 1906 August 21 - 1912 March 31 (Box 8)
  - Employee payroll book, 1913 November - 1917 July (Box 9)
- Series 4. Personnel, 1874-1941; 1990-018
  As titles of records suggests, several of these materials overlap others, but staff was not able to determine the reason for this.
  - Record of applications and service, 1881 March 21 - 1885 July 8 (Box 1)
    Includes a record of discharges described as a "Black List," 1884 - 1915.
  - Index of Employees, 1884-1915 (Box 1)
  - Record of application for employment, 1896 May 15 - 1900 October 5 (Box 1)
  - Employee payroll and service records, 1894-1914; 5 volumes and 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Employee service records, 1874-1915; 2 volumes and 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Employee service records, 1874-1914; 2 volumes and 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Employee biographies
    - 1921-1930, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - 1929-1934, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - 1931-1939, 6 folders (Box 5)
    - 1938-1941, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - 1939-1941, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - 1941-1944, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - Biographies of nurses hired, 1908-1926 (Box 7)
- Series 5. Patients, 1868-1984
  - 1990-018
    - Indexes, 2 volumes (Box 1-2)
      Gives patient's name and case number.
    - Reports of Re - Education and physical training classes, 1916-1932 (Box 3)
  - 2000-015
    - Files, 1962-1965 (discharge dates); 201 cubic feet (Box 901-1101)
  - 2010-010
    - Commitment papers, 1874-1916
      - Case numbers 1051-1250, 1851-1961, 1874-1880 (Box 4)
        Case numbers 1251-1450 were not transferred to the State Archives.
      - Case numbers 1962-2761, 1880-1883 (Box 5)
      - Case numbers 2762-3519, 1883-1885 (Box 6)
      - Case numbers 3520-4211, 1885-1887 (Box 7)
      - Case numbers 4212-4930, 1887-1899 (Box 8)
      - Case numbers 4931-5539, 1889-1891 (Box 9)
      - Case numbers 5540-6120, 11891-1892 (Box 10)
      - Case numbers 6122-6727, 1892-1894 (Box 11)
      - Case numbers 6728-7341, 1894-1895 (Box 12)
      - Case numbers 7342-7910, 1895-1897 (Box 13)
      - Case numbers 7911-8509, 1897-1898 (Box 14)
      - Case numbers 8510-9235, 1898-1900 (Box 15)
      - Case numbers 9236-9992, 1900-1902 (Box 16)
      - Case numbers 9993-10720, 1902-1903 (Box 17)
      - Case numbers 10721-11450, 1903-1905 (Box 18)
      - Case numbers 11451-12230, 1905-1907 (Box 19)
      - Case numbers 12231-12941, 1907-1909 (Box 20)
      - Case numbers 12942-13582, 1909-1910 (Box 21)
      - Case numbers 13583-14272, 1910-1912 (Box 22)
      - Case numbers 14273-14987, 1912-1914 (Box 23)
      - Case numbers 14988-15626, 1914-1915 (Box 24)
      - Case numbers 15627-15999, 1915-1916 (Box 25)
    - Admissions and discharges, 1868-1984
      The following were not transferred to the State Archives: Daily Summary no. 3, 1886 July - 1894 June; Admissions and discharges, 1904 January - 1909 November.
      - Patient register, 1868-1910; 1 volume (Box 26)
      - Daily summary no. 1, 1868 April - 1876 December; 1 volume (Box 26)
      - Daily summary no. 2, 1876 December - 1886 June; 1 volume (Box 26)
      - Daily summary no. 4, 1894 July - 1902 December; 1 volume (Box 27)
      - 1909 December - 1914 December, 1 volume (Box 27)
      - 1915 January - 1918 September, 1 volume (Box 27)
      - Patient daily register, Volume 1, 1918 October - 1923 December; 1 volume (Box Item 28)
        Contains case numbers 17173-19623.
      - Patient daily register, Volume 2, 1924 January - 1928 June; 1 volume (Box Item 29)
        Contains case numbers 19624-22072.
      - Patient daily register, Volume 3, 1928 July - 1932 March; 1 volume (Box Item 30)
        Contains case numbers 22073-24482.
      - Patient daily register, Volume 4, 1932 April - 1935 April; 1 volume (Box Item 31)
        Contains case numbers 24483-26894.
      - Patient daily register, Volume 5, 1935 May - 1938 February; 1 volume (Box Item 32)
        Contains case numbers 26895-29386.
      - Patient daily register, Volume 6, 1938 March - 1940 June; 1 volume (Box Item 33)
        Contains case numbers 29387-31845.
      - Patient daily register, Volume 7, 1940 July - 1942 October; 1 volume (Box Item 34)
        Contains case numbers 31846-33825.
      - Patient daily register, Volume 8, 1942 Novemnber - 1945 June; 1 volume (Box Item 35)
        Contains case numbers 33826-35771.
      - Patient daily register, Volume 9, 1945 July - 1947 October; 1 volume (Box Item 36)
        Contains case numbers 35772-37381.
      - Patient daily register, Volume 10, 1947 November - 1949 November; 1 volume (Box Item 37)
        Contains case numbers 37832-39921.
      - Patient daily register, Volume 11, 1949 December - 1951 May; 1 volume (Box Item 38)
        Contains case numbers 39922-41581.
      - Patient daily register, Volume 12, 1951 June - August; 1 volume (Box Item 39)
        Contains case numbers 41582-41872.
      - 1951 September - 1958 September (Box 40)
        Contains case numbers 41873-52130.
      - 1958 October - 1960 March (Box 41)
        Contains case numbers 52131-54560.
      - 1960 April - 1962 April (Box 42)
        Contains case numbers 54561-62366.
      - 1962 May - 1964 April (Box 43)
      - 1966 May - 1968 June (Box 45)
        Contains case numbers 68368-71781.
      - 1968 July - 1970 April (Box 46)
        Contains case numbers 71782-75415.
      - 1970 May - 1971 August (Box 47)
        Contains case numbers 75416-78123.
      - 1971 September - 1973 April (Box 48)
        Contains case numbers 78124-81029.
      - 1973 May - 1974 December (Box 49)
        Contains case numbers 81030-83903.
      - 1975 January - 1977 February (Box 50)
        Contains case numbers 83904-87223.
      - 1977 March - 1979 April (Box 51)
        Contains case numbers 87224-89958.
      - 1979 May - 1981 February (Box 52)
        Contains case numbers 89949-92039.
      - 1981 March - 1982 December (Box 53)
        Contains case numbers 92040-93937.
      - 1983 January - 1984 November (Box 54)
        Contains case numbers 93988-96041.
    - Case history books, 1873-1915
      Volumes 1, 2, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 18, 21, 23, 25, 26, 28, 33, 37, 38, 39, 41, 44 were not transferred to the State Archives.
      - Volume 3, 1873 October 1 - 1874 September 1 (Box Item 55)
        Contains case numbers 773-1005.
      - Volume 4, 1874 September 3 - 1875 October 23 (Box Item 56)
        Contains case numbers 1006-1226.
      - Volume 15, 1886 February 13 - Octobe 5 (Box Item 57)
        Contains case numbers 3638-3877.
      - Volume 16, 1886 October 7 - 1887 June 4 (Box Item 58)
        Contains case numbers 3878-4116.
      - Volume 17, 1887 June 6 - December 30 (Box Item 59)
        Contains case numbers 4117-4355.
      - Volume 19, 1888 August 9 - 1889 April 5 (Box Item 60)
        Contains case numbers 4595-4835.
      - Volume 20, 1889 April 5 - November 18 (Box Item 61)
        Contains case numbers 4836-5075.
      - Volume 22, 1890 July 24 - 1891 March 3 (Box Item 62)
        Contains case numbers 5316-5555.
      - Volume 24, 1891 Septembner 11 - 1892 May 14 (Box Item 63)
        Contains case numbers 5795-6033.
      - Volume 27, 1893 October 12 - 1894 June 14 (Box Item 64)
        Contains case numbers 6514-6756.
      - Volume 29, 1895 March 16 - September 9 (Box Item 65)
        Contains case numbers 6995-7234.
      - Volume 30, 1895 September 11 - 1896 March 28 (Box Item 66)
        Contains case numbers 7235-7473.
      - Volume 31, 1896 March 30 - October 27 (Box Item 67)
        Contains case numbers 7474-7713.
      - Volume 32, 1896 October 27 - 1897 June 15 (Box Item 68)
        Contains case numbers 7714-7952.
      - Volume 34, 1898 February 19 - September 12 (Box Item 69)
        Contains case numbers 8192-8430.
      - Volume 35, 1898 September 12 - 1899 April 21 (Box Item 70)
        Contains case numbers 8431-8669.
      - Volume 36, 1899 April 24 - November 8 (Box Item 71)
        Contains case numbers 8670-8922.
      - Volume 40, 1903 April 22 - 1904 June 17 (Box Item 72)
        Contains case numbers 10422-10919.
      - Volume 42, 1905 July 10 - 1906 September 7 (Box Item 73)
        Contains case numbers 11419-11915.
      - Volume 43, 1906 September 8 - 1907 November 26 (Box Item 74)
        Contains case numbers 22926-12417.
      - Volume 45, 1909 March - 1910 May 19 (Box Item 75)
        Contains case numbers 12918-13418.
      - Volume 46, 1910 May 20 - 1911 August 7 (Box Item 76)
        Contains case numbers 13419-13918.
      - Volume 47, 1911 August 11 - 1912 December 5 (Box Item 77)
        Contains case numbers 13919-14417.
      - Volume 48, 1912 December 5 - 1914 March 12 (Box Item 78)
        Contains case numbers 14418-14915.
      - Volume 49, 1914 March 13 - 1915 April 17 (Box Item 79)
        Contains case numbers 14916-15415.
      - Volume 50, 1915 April 17 - September 30 (Box Item 80)
        Contains case numbers 15416-15587.
      - Index (Box Item 81)
    - Patients within draft age, 1940-1946; 2 folders (Box 82)
- Series 6. Medical Staff Records, 1901-1991
  - 1990-018
    - Minutes of staff meetings, 2 volumes
      - 1901-1903 (Box 1)
      - 1916-1917 (Box 1)
    - Gross notes of brain dissections, circa 1935-1945; 1 book (Box 1)
    - List of operations, 1917-1951; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - List of lobotomy operations, 1946-1951; 1 folder (Box 1)
    - Doctors' order books, Ward 65, 1948-1951; 2 volumes (Box 2)
    - Connecticut cooperative lobotomy study - Syllabus of Exhibit, 1 folder (Box 3)
    - Manual of standard procedures, 1951 November; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - 1990-018
    - Admissions, 1959-1968 (Box 82)
      - 1959 January 1 - April 17, 1 volume (Box 82)
      - 1960 January 1 - 1961 January 3, 1 volume (Box 82)
      - 1961 January 1 - December 31, 1 volume (Box 82)
      - Dix Hall, 1962 April 3 - 1965 May 31; 1 volume (Box 82)
      - Dix Hall, 1964 October 27 - 1968 June 30; 1 volume (Box 82)
    - Day books, 1951-1954 (Box 82)
      - 1951 July 27 - 1952 November 11, 1 volume (Box 82)
      - 1952 November 11 - 1953 November 4, 1 volume (Box 82)
      - 1953 November 4 - 1954 September 21, 1 volume (Box 82)
    - Journals, 1951-1954 (Box 82)
      - 1951 February 28 - July 3, 1 volume (Box 82)
      - 1951 July 4 - November 18, 1 volume (Box 82)
      - 1951 November 19 - 1952 April 10, 1 volume (Box 82)
      - 1952 April 11 - 1952 September 6, 1 volume (Box 82)
      - 1952 September 7 - 1953 January 31, 1 volume (Box 82)
      - 1953 February 1 - 1953 June 29, 1 volume (Box 82)
      - 1953 November 26 - 1954 April 22, 1 volume (Box 82)
    - Morgue book, 1972-1991; 1 volume (Box 82)
    - Untitled, 1960-1972; 1 volume (Box 82)
      Contents: Cancelled numbers; Births, 1960-1966; Children admitted under 16, 1960-1972; Children discharged, 1960-1962; Day care, 1967-1971; Patients admitted for surgery only Section 18-52A, 1963-1965.
- Series 7. School of Nursing, 1904-1939; 1990-018
  - Graduate nurses record, 1904-1939; 4 folders (Box 1)
- Series 8. Miscellaneous, 1889-1976; 1990-018
  - 1990-018
    - Log of letters written ("Annex Views"), 1889-1891; 1 volume (Box 1)
    - Guest book, Woodward open house, 1976 October, 19 (Box 1)
    - Index, 1 small book (Box 1)
    - Selected historical documents (Box 2)
    - Design samples for 100th Anniversary medallion, 1967 (Box 2)
  - 1999-038
    - Practical nursing procedures, compiled by A.M. Nash, Principal of Training School, Connecticut State Hospital, Approved 1928 February; 1 booklet
      Stored in a shared box
- Series 9. Photographs, 1914-1967; 1999-183; 1 oversize flat box